Guide to the William Goldman papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
William Goldman Papers,
1949-1997
Goldman, William, 1931-
98 linear ft. ( 229 document boxes; 3 flat boxes; 1 mapcase).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
5018084
Biographical Note
William Goldman is best-know as a novelist, playwright and screenwriter. He was born in Chicago, Illinois in 1931. He received a BA in 1952 from Oberlin College and an MA from Columbia University in 1956. His first novel "Temple of Gold" was published in 1957. He went on to write several other novels including "Boys and Girls Together" (1964), "The Thing of It Is.. ." (1964); "The Princess Bride" (1974); "Marathon Man" (1975); and "The Color of Light" (1984).
Goldman began writing screenplays in 1965. He has been nominated for several screenwriting awards and has won Oscars for both "Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid" in 1970 and "All The President's Men" in 1977. Other screenplays written by Goldman include "Harper" (1966); "Marathon Man" (1976); "The Princess Bride" (1987); "Misery" (1990); and "Absolute Power" (1997). In 1985 Goldman was the recipient of the Laurel Award for lifetime achievement in screenwriting.
Goldman's nonfiction works include a book about the Broadway theater, "The Season" (1969) one about his beloved sports; "Wait Until Next Year" (1988), with Mike Lupica; "Hype and Glory" (1990) about the Cannes Film Festival and the Miss America Pageant; and the highly acclaimed "Adventures of the Screen Trade" (1983), his definitive and personal view of Hollywood and the profession. Goldman was a regular columnist for "New York Magazine" between 1990 and 1994 and has written for "Premiere".
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, notes, drafts, photographs, tapes, clippings, printed material, and memorabilia covering the career of William Goldman.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 10 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Education and Early Writing
Series IV: Manuscripts
Series V: Screenplays by Others
Series VI: Notes, Clippings and Ephemera
Series VII: Photographs
Series VIII: Audio Visual
Series IX: Memorabilia
Series X: Printed
Subjects
Goldman, William, 1931-; Literature, Modern.; Motion picture authorship.; Motion picture industry--United States.; Motion pictures and literature.; Novelists--United States.; Screenwriters--United States.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 1-212; 214-229. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Gift of William Goldman
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Evans, Robert To: William Goldman, [Hollywood, Ca.], 15 Oct. 1974, (1p. t.l.s, with envelope) (Box 213)
  - Grisham, John To: William Goldman, [North Garden, Va.], 5 Dec. 1994, (1p. t.l.s, with notes by Goldman on verso) (Box 213)
  - Hamill, Pete To: William Goldman, Encino, Ca., 3 Jan. 1974, (1p. t.l.s, with envelope) (Box 213)
    [6 marked books added from Hype and Glory box 165]
  - Hill, George Roy To: William Goldman, [New York], 29 Oct. 1982, (2p. t.l.s, with envelope) (Box 213)
  - Hill, George Roy To: William Goldman, [Beverly Hills], 13 August 1968, (6p. t.l.s, with envelope) (Box 213)
  - Hill. George Roy To: William Goldman, [Hollywood, Ca.], 21 Oct. 1969, (1p. t.l.s. ) (Box 213)
  - Jovanovich, William To: William Goldman, [New York.], 13 April 1970, (2p. t.l.s, with envelope) (Box 213)
  - Kael, Pauline To: William Goldman, [New York.], [14 Jan. 1970], (1p. a.l.s, with related letter) (Box 213)
  - Kerr, Walter To: William Goldman, [Larchmont, N.Y.], 10 Oct. 1969, (1p. t.l.s, with envelope) (Box 213)
  - Lester, Richard To: William Goldman, [Twickenham, UK], 10 Nov. 1978, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 213)
  - Manilow, Barry To: William Goldman, [Beverly Hills], 8 May 1984, (1p. a.l.s, with related photos and envelope) (Box 213)
  - Manilow, Barry To: Bill [Goldman], [Beverly Hills], 9 May 1985, (1p. a.l.s, with envelope) (Box 213)
  - Meredith, Burgess To: Bill Goldman, [Malibu], 6 Feb. 1978, (1p. a.l.s. ) (Box 213)
  - Perot, H Ross To: William Goldman, [Dallas], Dec. 1980 - June 1981, (2 t.l.s, with related photocopies) (Box 213)
  - Redford, Robert To: William Goldman, New York, Wengen Switzerland and Geneva Switzerland, n.d., and April 1970 - Nov. 1979, (1p. a.l.s., (with envelope and notes in Goldman's hand); a.l.s, with photo); telegram) (Box 213)
  - Reiner, Carl To: William Goldman, [Hollywodd, Ca.], Sept. 1969 - Oct. 1969, (2 t.l.s, with related materials) (Box 213)
  - Simon, Neil To: Bill [Goldman], [Hollywood, Ca.], 14 Sept. [1969], (1p. t.l.s, with envelope) (Box 213)
  - Sondheim, Stephen To: William Goldman, [New York], 29 March 1977, (1p. telegram) (Box 213)
  - Towne, Robert To: William Goldman, Malibu, 29 March 1977, (1p. telegram) (Box 213)
  - Valenti, Jack To: William Goldman, Washington, DC. Feb. 1970 - March 1977, (3 telegrams) (Box 213)
  - Warner, Jack To: William Goldman, [Century City, Ca.], 8 April 1970, (1p. t.l.s, with envelope) (Box 213)
  - Yates, Peter To: Baron Eric de Rothschild, London, 2 April 1991, (1p. facsimilie (with related) (Box 213)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  Arranged on a project basis
  - Subseries 2.1 Adventures in the Screen Trade
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1983 - 1986, (4 t.l.s, ) (Box 214, Folder 1)
      [The following series of arranged correspondence is organized on a "project" basis. ]
  - Subseries 2.2 All the President's Men
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1974 - 1977 (Box 214, Folder 2)
      [This folder contains mostly congratulatory notes for his screenplay Oscar]
  - Subseries 2.3 Brothers
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1986 - 1987 (Box 214, Folder 3)
      [Mostly letters pertaining to the publication of the novel]
  - Subseries 2.4 Butch and Sundance, the Early Years
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1977 - 1979 (Box 214, Folder 4)
      [Production oriented letters ]
  - Subseries 2.5 Chaplin
    - Kathryn Sommer To: William Goldman, Los Angeles, 28 August 1991, (1p. facsimilie, ) (Box 214, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2.6 The Color of Light
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1984 - 1985 (Box 214, Folder 6)
      [Letters and materials pertanent to the publication of the novel]
  - Subseries 2.7 Control
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1981 - 1984 (Box 214, Folder 7)
      [Letters pertaing to the publication of the novel]
  - Subseries 2.8 Father's Day
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1971 (Box 214, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2.9 Ghost and the Darkness
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1989 - 1995 (Box 214, Folder 9)
      [Production and script correspondence]
  - Subseries 2.10 The Great Waldo Pepper
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1972 (Box 214, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 2.11 Heat
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1985 (Box 214, Folder 11)
      [Personal letters regarding the book]
  - Subseries 2.12 The Hot Rock
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1971 - 1973 (Box 214, Folder 12)
      [Script and production notes]
  - Subseries 2.13 Hype and Glory
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1988-1990 (Box 214, Folder 13)
      [From Miss America officials and Cannes officials]
  - Subseries 2.14 Magic
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1976 (Box 214, Folder 14)
      [Publishers correspondence]
  - Subseries 2.15 Marathon Man
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1974 - 1976 (Box 214, Folder 15)
      [Publishers correspondence and others]
  - Subseries 2.16 Marathon Man
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1982 (Box 214, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 2.17 Memoires of an Invisible Man
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1991 (Box 214, Folder 17)
      [Mostly legal papers pertaining to Goldman's screen credit status]
  - Subseries 2.18 The Princess Bride
    - Various People To: William Goldman and George Roy Hill, [v.p.], 1982 - 1987 (Box 214, Folder 18)
      [Letters pertaining to the production and other film tie-ins]
  - Subseries 2.19 The Princess Bride
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1974 - 1993 (Box 214, Folder 19)
      [Publisher's letters and notes of enthusiasm]
  - Subseries 2.20 The Silent Gondoliers
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1983 - 1985 (Box 214, Folder 20)
      [Correspondence from publishers and others]
  - Subseries 2.21 Tinsel
    - John Brady To: William Goldman, n.p., 1979 - 1981 (Box 214, Folder 21)
  - Subseries 2.22 Tom Horn
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1977 (Box 214, Folder 22)
  - Subseries 2.23 Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], ca. 1950s (Box 214, Folder 23)
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], ca. early 1960s (Box 214, Folder 24)
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], ca. late 1960s (Box 214, Folder 25)
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], ca. 1970s (Box 214, Folder 26)
    - Various People To: William Goldman, [v.p.], ca. 1980s (Box 214, Folder 27)
    - [?] To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1962 - 1977 (Box 214, Folder 28)
      [Congratulatory telegrams without names]
    - [?] To: William Goldman, [v.p.], 1957 - 1980s (Box 214, Folder 29)
      [Corrspondence with unknown persons]
    - Kelly, Betty To: William Goldman, [n.p.], Sept. 1978 - April 1982 (Box 215, Folder 1)
      [Betty Kelly was William Goldman's editor at Delacorte Press Arranged by correspondent]
    - Haydn, Hiram To: William Goldman, [n.p.], 1959 - 1973 (Box 215, Folder 2)
      [Hiram Haydn was William Goldman's publisher at Harcout Brace Jovanovich]
    - Claiborne, Ross To: William Goldman, [n.p.], 1973 - 1976 (Box 215, Folder 3)
      [Ross Claiborne was Editorial Director at Dell Publishing]
  - Subseries 2.24 Fan Mail/Contest
    - Requests for the "reunion scene" from The Princess Bride. (Box 49, Folder 1 & 2)
- Series III: Education and Early Writings
  Includes his Columbia University M.A. thesis
  - The Shape of the World. t.ms.; The Good Things of the Earth;. a.ms.; Assorted writing exercises. a.ms.; The Two Bears. t.ms.; Untitled fragment. t.ms.; Whom the Gods would Destroy.... t.ms.; M is for the Million Things. t.ms; What Lamp Has Destiny to Guide Her Little Children Stumbling in the Dark. t.ms., [n.p.], 1949-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - How We Are Clothed; a.ms.; Untitled fragment; t.ms.; Something About a Soldier; a.ms.; Scrutiny of a Mess; t.ms.; Say Hello to the Oak Trees; a.ms.; Between Men and Dogs;; Various writing exercises; a.ms.; Untitled fragment; t.ms., [n.p.], 1949-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled story; t.ms.; Untitled fragment; t.ms; Happy Thirtieth Birthday! J & D: a bound collection of t.ms. essays; A friendly Atmosphere;; Untitled fragment; t.ms.; Unitled fragment; t.ms.; Thlunk; t.ms.; The Simple Pleasures of the Rich; t.ms.; Orphan; t.ms.; Untitled essay; t.ms.; Untitled; t.ms., [n.p.], 1949-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Always Leon. 3 t.ms.; Friday Graduation. 3 t.ms.; Prayer. t.ms., [n.p.], 1949-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4 & 5)
  - The Comedy of Manners in America, [New York], 1956, (2 t.ms. drafts (with ms. notes & marginalia) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    [William Goldman's Columbia University Thesis]
- Series IV: Manuscripts
  - Subseries 4.1 Screenplays
      - Draft of short story and autograph notes for Flowers for Algernon: Good Old Charley Gordon (Box 10, Folder 10)
        [Based on a short story by Daniel Keyes]
      - Flowers for Algernon: Good Old Charley Gordon; includes draft of short story, [n.p.], 1964 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Draft and related materials for Masquarade (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Drafts, notes and ephemera for Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid (Box 10, Folder 4 - 7)
      - First draft of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid., ( Carbon and typescript drafts, ) (Box 11, Folder 2 - 5)
      - Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid, ( Color coded page revisions, ) (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid, ( Final notes, ) (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid, ( Draft notes and production breakdown, ) (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid; --Ephemera: magazine and newpaper clippings, brass belt buckle; award materials from the MPAA (Oscar) and others. (Box 12, Folder 2 - 6)
      - Archer based on Moving Target by Ross McDonald, ( Typescript draft with autograph notes, ) (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Archer, ( Drafts, ) (Box 13, Folder 1 - 4)
      - In the Spring the War Ended, (3 drafts, ) (Box 13, Folder 4 - 7)
      - In the Spring the War Ended, (2 drafts, ) (Box 14, Folder 1 - 2)
      - The Thing Of It Is with music by Stephen Sondheim, ( Drafts (all nearly final), ) (Box 15, Folder 1 - 3)
        [ Folder 1 contains a file of story notes with working title:Bongiorno Brummell]
      - The Thing Of It Is aka That's Life, (Various drafts, ) (Box 16, Folder 1 - 3)
      - That's Life; --Contains story notes with the working title Bongiorno Brummell (Box 15, Folder 4 - 7)
      - The Chill, ( Notes and drafting materials, ) (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - The Chill, ( First draft, ) (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - The Chill, [n.p.], 1967, ( Draft, ) (Box 17, Folder 1 & 2)
      - The Chill, ( Second draft, ) (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - The Chill, ( First final rewrites, ) (Box 17, Folder 4 & 5)
      - The Chill, ( Second final rewrites, ) (Box 17, Folder 6 - 8)
      - The Piano Man adapted from his own novel Father's Day, (Various drafts, ) (Box 35, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Two copies of the script for an untitled musical with screenplay by Goldman and score by Stephen Sondheim, [New York], June 19990, (2 binders stamped "UNTITLED", ) (Box 225)
    - THE HOT ROCK
      - Various drafts of the screenplay The Hot Rock; --This script had the working titles of "Four for the Money " and "The Masterminds", [n.p.], 1970-1971 (Box 37, Folder 1 - 6)
      - Drafts of The Hot Rock (Box 38, Folder 1 - 4)
      - The Hot Rock: Drafts of scripts and research materials (Box 39, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Script pages The Hot Rock (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Color coded draft of The Hot Rock (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - THE GREAT WALDO PEPPER
      - The Great Waldo Pepper: Second draft, July 29, 1972 (Box 41, Folder 1)
      - The Great Waldo Pepper: First final rewrite, February 15, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 2)
      - The Great Waldo Pepper: Second final rewrites, July-August, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 3 - 5)
      - The Great Waldo Pepper: Final screenplays, August 22, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 6 - 7)
      - The Great Waldo Pepper: Script notes, production records, 1973 (Box 42, Folder 1)
      - Drafts of The Great Waldo Pepper (Box 42, Folder 2 - 5)
    - PAPILLON
      - Papillon materials; Dry Guillotine by Rene Belbenoit; Papillion by Henri Charriere (2 copies); notes and early drafts of the screeplay Papillion by William Goldman (uncredited) (Box 44, Folder 5 - 7)
      - Papillion final draft (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - THE PRINCESS BRIDE
      - First drafts of the screenplay The Princess Bride (Box 49, Folder 3 - 6)
      - Princess Bride; notes; first and second drafts of the screenplay (Box 50, Folder 1 - 8)
      - Drafts of the screenplay Princess Bride; fan mail, reviews and publisher's material for the novel Princess Bride (Box 51, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Revised drafts of the screenplay The Princess Bride; Notes on script; Copy of American Film December 1983 containing Princess Bride reference (Box 52, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Final drafts and production notes concerning Rob Reiner as director of the film (Box 53, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Final drafts of the screenplay The Princess Bride some with annotations; Folder 54 - 8 contains a small folder of promotional material (Box 54, Folder 1 - 8)
      - Revised final drafts, May 3, 1986 (Box 55, Folder 1 - 5)
      - Production notes (Box 55, Folder 6)
      - Revised draft with storyboards (Box 56, Folder 2)
      - Final draft of screenplay (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - THE STEPFORD WIVES
      - First draft of screenplay The Stepford Wives by W. Goldman (Box 58, Folder 6)
      - Stepford Wives drafts and other materials (Box 59, Folder 1 - 6)
      - Stepford Wives: Drafts of the screenplay and MPAA voting materials for the Academy Awards 1973 Academy Awards1973 voting material and wine related research for the screenplay Year of the Comet (Box 60, Folder 1 - 5)
    - THE YEAR OF THE COMET
      - First drafts of the screenplay Year of the Comet (Box 62, Folder 5 - 7)
      - Copies of the second draft of The Year of the Comet (Box 63, Folder 1 - 6)
      - Research materials and copies of the third draft of The Year of the Comet (Box 64, Folder 1-6)
      - Copies of the third, forth and seventh draft of The Year of the Comet (Box 65, Folder 1 - 6)
      - Seventh and eighth draft of Year of the Comet (Box 66, Folder 1 & 2)
    - MARATHON MAN
      - First draft of the screenplay (Box 68, Folder 6)
      - Revised draft of Marathon Man (Box 68, Folder 7)
      - Drafts of the screenplay (Box 69, Folder 1 - 7)
      - First drafts of the screenplay (Box 69, Folder 1 - 3)
      - Second drafts of Marathon Man (Box 69, Folder 4 - 6)
      - Third draft (Box 69, Folder 7)
      - Drafts of the screenplay (Box 70, Folder 1 - 8)
      - Third draft (Box 70, Folder 1 & 2)
      - Notes and pages Marathon Man (Box 70, Folder 3)
      - Fourth draft (Box 70, Folder 4 - 8)
      - Marathon Man (Box 71, Folder 1 - 4)
      - Clippings, ads, book tie-in (Box 71, Folder 1)
    - TOM HORN
      - Mr. Horn notes, and pages (Box 72, Folder 2)
      - Teleplay and notes (Box 72, Folder 3 & 4)
    - ALL THE PRESIDENT'S MEN
      - Drafts of the William Goldman script (Box 79, Folder 1 - 6)
      - Various versions of the second draft of the screenplay All the President's Men (Box 80, Folder 1 - 4)
      - Script pages (Box 81, Folder 3 & 4)
      - Copies of revised screenplay (Box 81, Folder 5 & 6)
      - Various copies of the script, 1975 (Box 82, Folder 1 - 5)
    - THE SEA KINGS
      - First and second drafts (Box 104, Folder 1 - 6)
      - Second and third drafts, 1991-1994 (Box 105, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Third and forth drafts (Box 106, Folder 1 - 4)
    - FLORA QUICK, DEAD OR ALIVE
      - Screenplay and City in Fear by Albert Ruben, 1979; Drafts of the screenplays (Box 115, Folder 1 - 5)
    - THE NATIONAL PASTIME/DAMAGES
      - Draft pages, second draft; notes and clippings (Box 187, Folder 1 - 4)
    - MAVERICK/LAST ACTION HERO
      - Drafts, notes and final draft (Box 199, Folder 1 - 5)
  - Subseries 4.2: Novels
    - Untitled; t.ms.; The Other Way; t.ms.; When There Was Glory In It; t.ms.; Untitled; t.ms.; On The Diamond;; Survival; t.ms.; Untitled; t.ms.; A Great Big House In Brooklyn; t.ms.; Something From Tiffany's; t.ms.; Fragment plus a.ms notes; Fragment; a.ms.; A Box of Candy; t.ms.; Still Good; t.ms.; Untitled t.ms with a.ms notes; Naomi, Like In The Bible; t.ms.; The Method; t.ms.; Untitled; t.ms.; Flight; t.ms.; Untitled; t.ms.; Jump and I'll Catch You; a.ms.; Beer; t.ms.; The Ice Ceam Eat; t.ms.; Royalty; t.ms.; Thumbnail sketches for plays or novels; t.ms.; 6 poems; t.ms.; Roaylty; t.ms., 1949-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - THE TEMPLE OF GOLD
      - First draft, ( T.ms., ) (Box 3, Folder 1)
        [Includes autograph notes]
      - Draft materials, ( T.ms., ) (Box 3, Folder 2)
        [Includes autograph notes and publisher's editorial notes]
      - Late draft, ( T.ms. ) (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Late draft, ( T.ms. ) (Box 3, Folder 4)
        [Includes publisher's advertising material]
      - Final draft, [1956] -1957, ( T.ms., ) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - YOUR TURN TO CURTSEY, MY TURN TO BOW
      - [First] draft of Your Turn to Curtsey, My Turn to Bow, ( Notes and t.ms., ) (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Draft, with autograph notes (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - SOLDIER IN THE RAIN
      - Typescript and autograph notes and drafts of the novel a.k.a. A Few Days In Between (Box 4, Folder 2 - 7)
    - AFTER HARDBODY & JEWISH GIRLS MAKE THE BEST HUSBANDS
      - After Hardbody and related material; Jewish Girls Make the Best Husbands ms. pages and related material; Early writing and notes ca. 1971; Jewish Girls Make the Best Husbands Draft (Box 9, Folder 5 - 8)
    - THE THING OF IT IS
      - Drafts (Box 14, Folder 3 - 5)
      - Reviews (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - THE CHILL
      - Ross McDonald Paperback marked up by William Goldman (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - THE SEASON/FATHER'S DAY
      - Clipped/photocopied reviews of The Season and drafts of the novel Father's Day aka Pierre (Box 33, Folder 1 - 6)
      - Variois drafts of Father's Day (Box 33, Folder 2 - 6)
      - Drafts and proofs, 1969-1971 (Box 34, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Clippings/photostats reviews (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - THE PIANO MAN
      - Second draft, 1986 (Box 36, Folder 1)
      - Advance proof of The Goodbye Look by Ross MacDonald (Box 36, Folder 2)
      - W.G's notes on The Goodbye Look and a hardbound copy of The Hot Rock by Donald Westlake (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - THE PRINCESS BRIDE
      - Notes and prose drafts (Box 42, Folder 2 - 6)
      - Various printer's drafts of the novel (Box 47, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Publication materials; contest materials; requests for the "reunion scene" (Box 48, Folder 2 - 7)
      - Princess Bride (Box 49, Folder 1 - 6)
      - Revised draft for Ballentine Books (Box 56, Folder 3)
      - Materials relating to an audio version (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - MARATHON MAN
      - Research materials (Box 66, Folder 4)
      - Rough draft (Box 66, Folder 5)
      - Typed and carbon first drafts of the novel (Box 66, Folder 6 & 7)
      - Various typed drafts of the novel, including a publisher's proof (Box 67, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Drafts (Box 68, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Edited draft of the novel (Box 68, Folder 1)
    - WIGGER
      - Notes (Box 71, Folder 2)
      - Draft, proof and publisher's materials (Box 71, Folder 3 & 4)
    - HEAT
      - Various drafts and proofs of the novel (Box 95, Folder 3 - 6)
    - THE COLOR OF LIGHT
      - Proofs (Box 130, Folder 1 - 3)
    - BROTHERS
      - Novel and screenplay, 1986-1987 (Box 139, Folder 1 - 7)
      - Proof (Box 139, Folder 5)
    - MARATHON MAN
      - Proof (Box 139, Folder 4)
    - THE SILENT GONDOLIERS
      - Illustrations (Box 140, Folder 7)
    - THE TEMPLE OF GOLD/YOUR TURN TO CURTSEY, MY TURN TO BOW
      - Drafts (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 4.3: Plays
    - Thumbnail sketches for plays, 1949-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Madonna and Child by James and William Goldman (2 drafts); Blood, Sweat and Stanley Poole by James and William Goldman (Box 5, Folder 4 - 6)
    - Now I am Six (2 drafts); Something Blue (3 drafts); Notes for stories and plays; Nagurski, [n.p.], [ca. 1962] (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - No Way to Treat a Lady by Seymour Krenzer and Miles McGee (2 drafts) Something Blue (3 drafts); notes for stories and plays; Nagurski!; Notes, reports and drafting materials pertaining to No Way to Treat a Lady (Box 6, Folder 6 - 8)
  - Subseries 4.4: Short Stories
    - The Blossom and the Bough; t.ms.; Did You Like the Flowers? t.ms.; 4 Drafts of Theft; t.ms.; 5 Drafts of Orphan; t.ms. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Three Cheers for the Prince of Morocco; t.ms.; Stroll; t.ms.; Untitled; t.ms.; The Admitted Impediment; t.ms.; 3 Drafts of Tale for a Rainy Afternoon; t.ms.; Untitled; t.ms.; Hair of the Dog; t.ms. (Box 2, Folder 3)